this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is the chanson Asia
from software engineering radio today
I'm speaking with max noon Hoffer max
tena offer is a mathematician turned
database developer in his academic
career he has worked for 16 years on the
development and implementation of new
algorithms in computer algebra recently
he has returned from University of st.
Andrews where he was a lecturer to
Germany he has shifted his focus now to
seek no sequel databases and now helps
to develop
Arango DB he has spoken at international
conferences including O'Reilly of
architecture London J on the beach mezzo
scorn in Seattle among many others
welcome to software engineering radio
max hello so today we will be talking
about all the significant aspects of
multi model databases in general and
rango DB in specific rate so max let's
start with something basic and I just
wanted to I know that no sequel
databases have a lot of definitions I
just wanted to get your perspective on
how would you define no sequel database
is that it does not to SQL sequel but
essentially the term cannot really be
defined because it covers by now such a
wide variety of completely different
data stores that basically the only
thing you can say it is not just
relational database and if you know what
happens in this space then you cannot
even say that you relax asset semantics
or whatever because many no sequel data
although they don't do a relational and
they don't do sequels ad transactions
and adjoins and all the rest of it
so therefore the term doesn't have a
proper definition right right so yeah I
mean no sequel databases do have a like
a hazy definition because it encompasses
a lot so what are the different types of
no sequel databases okay so first one
dimension you can distinguish is the
different data models they are not only
relational databases but you have
document databases you have graph
databases you have just key value stores
you have column in your databases you
have even time series databases and I
probably forget a lot of these things so
the data model aspect is one defining
factor and here there's even something
like run baby which is a multi model
they're they're very supporting multiple
data models but the other big aspect is
the kind of current ease that data store
is giving to you and again this is the
same stiff independent from the data
model and a lot of no sequel databases
have chosen to offer more availability
promises as opposed to consistent
because this consistency promises and
that's just not a binary choice but it's
a whole spectrum of possibilities and
that's a secondary dimension of
differences so I would say there's data
model differences and there is
consistency guarantees and other
guarantees differences and that is
essentially where the difficulty finds
what type of data stored about doing it
makes sense like the data modeling and
like you said consistency guarantees are
the two defining criterias for any no
sequel database so like you talked about
different types I just wanted to get
into a few of them and understand what
they are let's start with document store
we did
show on MongoDB which I have put in the
show notes I just wanted to understand
how would you define a document store so
first of all with document or usually
means of JSON documents that's a highly
recursive data structure quite simple in
that syntax but quite powerful because
we can do lots of different data
structures with it now a document store
with the database which stores document
and the analogy to the traditional
database world is probably that adoption
and corresponds to a row in a table and
what is a table corresponds to a
collection of documents in a document
store so the thing is every row in a
table has to have the same format and
the same a to same types of entries in
the columns but in a document store on
every single document in the same
collection can have a different
structure and that is what is one of the
big strengths of adoption database
I see so that also means that you can I
think one other thing which documents
tools are good at is creating bunch of
secondary indexes on different
attributes in the JSON payload which we
are storing in the in the collection is
that correct it is that a correct
statement that's right exactly structure
in a collection you can still ask for
secondary indexes you have sorted
indexes you have hash indexes you have
things like geo indexes or full-text
indexes and what you do you specify this
should be on this and that attribute of
all the documents in this collection and
obviously the production will store the
index has to be prepared that this
attribute is sometimes there and
sometimes not because the documents can
have different different structure in
the same collection
great so moving over to the next type of
no sequel database which I wanted to
talk about was the graph database so
we did a show on neo4j which is the
episode 194 and I have also listed in
the show notes so again how would you
define a graph database right so first
of all we have to clear clear what
graphs are across in this context are
things consisting of vertices and edges
so the vertices are somehow nodes in in
the graph and the edges always go from
one vertex to another so it's
essentially a kind of relation between
the buttons between the vertices now a
graph database not only stores such
graphs but also makes it possible to do
graph queries so let's understand what
the typical graph query is usually when
you have a graph and let's make an
example for example a social network
where one person follows another say on
Twitter or whatever that would be the
typical graph because the people would
be the vertices and there would be an
edge from person a to b if a follows B
now the typical questions for such
graphs are start at one point maybe a
person and explore the vicinity in the
graph see who this person is following
and maybe who they are following and so
on and go pérignon defined number of
steps essentially and so that is what it
Roth Curry does it starts in a point in
the graph and follows edges to see what
other vertices can be reached and so
what makes a rafter a basic graph
database is really did it come to this
kind of graph traversals right so can
you tell us that why is such kind of a
traverse are difficult to do in a
relational database
yes so the usual idea you do when you
store graph in relational database you
would have one table for the vertices
and another table for the edges and
every edge would simply refer to true
what is is by for an he and that's it
that's okay for storing the graph but
the moment you want to follow
path in the graph following the edges of
depth say between five and ten you are
in deep trouble with relational database
because you not have to do a query which
does five to ten stacked joints that is
something which can first of all very
very difficult it's very difficult to
express in sequel and when you run it it
is quite inefficient and graph database
has typically a good language to express
such questions and then a good engine to
quickly retrieve the results right so we
will come back to the graph databases
and discuss in more details how a native
graph database like Arango DB makes such
queries faster in more details but for
now I wanted to quickly discuss the next
type of no sequel database we have done
which is a key value store we have done
shows on Cassandra and Voldemort DB in
the past I wanted to know how would you
define a key value store
well a value stores in a sense the most
simple of all that our models the only
possibility it does it Maps a certain
key space through values and values are
usually opaque to the database and can
be tracer rounds but they can also be
just binary data and the only community
possibility this database of us is to
look up keys and find the values
sometimes the key space is sorted and
you can also do range queries on keys
but the idea is always the same you look
up keys and find the corresponding
values that's all you can do but since
this is quite limiting with respect to
the varying it allows for very efficient
implementation and for a very very good
scalability I see so the scaling and
partitioning becomes very easy because
there is just one key on which you can
or rather one index on which you can
look up it's not trivial to add a
secondary index
or rather might not even make sense to
add a secondary index to a key value
store which which actually also makes
from what I understand
scaling easier exactly for scaling you
can simply sharp by the value of the key
you've ashtray a hashed value for the
key or you can do red shaadi and since
the database doesn't know what the value
of data is all about it doesn't
understand it there is no possibility to
add any kind of secondary indexes in
general and the advanced scanning is
easy you can just compute where would
the value for that key be and then ask
the pros pondok shot is a search engine
no sequel database or is that not
different than a document store with
full-text indexing that implements
relevant search on the text indices what
do you think about that okay first of
all if something is just a search engine
it's usually not a database at all okay
because things like consistency
guarantees and transactional behavior
and taking efficient transactional right
loads and so on are all things which I
would attribute to a database but the
search engine doesn't really have to
have that you so you can almost have a
search engine which takes an enormous
amount of time to ingest data doesn't
offer any kind of transactional finality
but once you have indexed it it can
retrieve and find stuff in a very
flexible way so that's the sweet spot of
a search engine
now of course nowadays the the borders
between the world of databases and the
world of search engine has become
somewhat fuzzy that is because there are
more and more databases and one more
advanced search
like for example around OTP was wrong so
but then also traditional search engines
allow for online notification and even
for transactions sometimes so they move
towards the space of databases but I
think it's still solid advice to not
trust a search engine as a primary
source and primary place to keep your
data
I say yeah that's a that's an
interesting point that search engine are
more suited for read-only workload after
the data has been ingested by a
background ETL job rather than databases
with support stronger right semantics
like acid guarantees which a search
engine won't have so apart from so we
have covered now three different types
of no sequel databases so apart from
that there two other database types
which I quickly wanted to discuss was
time series database and white column
databases so can you tell us like a
brief description of what they are yeah
first time students database is
specialized to ingest data from a time
series that is a stream of incoming data
and as always when we talk about a data
model we have to talk about the
tree-ring possibilities as well and for
example what time series databases are
very good is first of all ingest a high
volume of time series data and secondly
offer query possibilities like having a
sliding window on the data and do some
kind of action relation just over that
window but then of course slide it over
time
so a typical application would be you
ingest the quotes while some stock
exchange and you would like to be able
to have some kind of aggregation over
the last 24 hours
and keep that update up to date all the
time so that's a
a different data model which is required
to offer that kind of possibilities and
cornerstone is essentially a possibility
to store on tables but there is in most
relational databases you are mostly
interested to to retrieve full rows a
corner store is optimized to very very
quickly run through a column of the
table so essentially when a relation
database stores data it does so row by
row and the column master would do it
column by column such that you have a
high amount of data locality when you go
down column and so there are just
optimized for different theories right
that's an interesting point which you
brought up I it's with columnar
databases there is always this confusion
regarding white column databases like
Cassandra or HBase and like complete
truly column inner databases where the
database also is laid out in the column
format rather than row format so then
would I use one over the other typical
form for analytics where you have a huge
amount of data and you are interested in
aggregations of a single column then you
would use a proper column a store and
these white corner stores are useful for
other purposes as well so you can have
multiple views there and also use it
more like a relational database you
don't get the acid semantics usually and
you still get some of the optimization
possibilities for a proper column a
store but you have more flexible
possibilities to also clearly multiple
columns at the same time I see I see
great so now that we have firmly
established no sequel database gone over
different types of it my next question
to you is about polyglot modeling and
persistence how would you define
polyglot persistence that's an
interesting one because I would define
politic persistence as using the right
data model for the right part of your
project this is not how it was
traditionally defined traditionally it
was defined as using the right data
store for the right part of your system
now that of course assumes essentially
that if every data store just has a
single data model then the two
definitions are the same on the other
hand with the advent of multimodal
databases which support multiple data
models my definition with the usage of
the right data model for the right
purpose makes more sense in my opinion
because it essentially says that that
you should look at your data project you
should look at different parts and you
freely choose the right data model for
the purpose at work can you just give
you an example if you would do an
e-commerce system you would probably use
a key value store for the shopping
basket in your volunteer system for your
product catalog you might use at auction
in store and for your recommendation
engine you would use a rough database
and that all makes sense and now the
question is how many data stores do you
need to do all that and the traditional
polyglot approach means that you have
separate data stores for each of these
parts and now with multiple databases
you have more possibilities I see that
was a pretty good description of
polyglot persistence and I think you
also covered the e-commerce example
which I wanted to go over so you
describe different use cases in an
e-commerce scenario where all these
three different types of databases
document key value and graph will be
used but if if I have to generalize the
use cases of these three particular
types of no sequel databases which is to
say that when would I choose one over
the other
what are the criterias which someone who
is doing a data modeling should before I
get this question quite often and
there's actually quite simple a
universal answer to that don't look at
the data first but look at the questions
you have about the data and the queries
first you for example notice that like
in the shopping basket scenario the only
question is
give me the shopping basket of customer
XYZ and you notice that the only type of
theory is this kind of key-value Luka
then you know you need to keep a low
store and if you further find out that
you need a high availability and high
scalability then you know you haven't
found the right item on the other hand
if you notice that you have a very
complicated questions in a
recommendation engine you know you want
to look at things like look at all the
items one customer bought then look at
maybe another customer who bought the
same item and then maybe looking further
around for these people bought and what
preferences they might have and do a
deep analysis of all this data and in
the end come up with a recommendation
for user PE by looking at user name this
sounds a lot more like exploring linked
data and doing complicated queries in a
graph so therefore the graph model is
probably more suitable and if you then
decide how to store the data and then
probably things fall into place and you
know what to do so that's what my advice
is always look at the queries you need
and the questions you want to answer
about your data and once you have that
you are 50% of the way to start to find
the right data model great so one other
thing which I wanted to ask because we
talked about using these three different
types of no sequel databases and and
scenarios under which or use cases for
which you will use them when would I
want to use a relational database over
all of these three date database no
sequel databases which we just discussed
yeah so if all your data feeds on one
machine you don't need a very high value
resilient setup and you you need acid
semantics then a relational databases is
still pretty good so it's not bad what
has what has been researched in 30 years
of database research it is more if you
have further requirements which a
relational database cannot fulfill like
very high scalability different data
models for different types of queries
and so on where you are somehow forced
to leave behind the relational world so
if you have rather homogeneous data like
say a customer database where you know
what kind of data you want to store or
their customers and you might have
something which you can put in an extra
table like their addresses then the
relational model is perfectly fine but
if you need higher scalability if you
need graph reversals or if you need to
very high throughput with key value cops
I see so on what you said how would a
shard a relational database compare with
let's say any other no sequel database
because one thing which you brought out
is that the scale it's difficult to
scale a relational database so how if we
shard it across multiple machines will
that not work as good as a no sequel
database no I don't think so
the relational model uses data
normalization that's in principle a good
idea but essentially it means that you
have to massage your data until it fits
it to tables that is all fine and that
has good properties and there's a lot of
mathematical theorems about that so far
except that the moment you have somehow
taken apart or data and massage it into
tables
you then have to decide how to short
these tables and
what you then will need its drone
operations so the moment you have done
the data novelizations and you have put
everything into tables to do queries you
will have to do joins and if you have a
distributed data set then joins can be a
challenge mainly because if everything
is on one computer you can very quickly
find the paths you have to join together
but in addition to the system you might
run into the problem then two things you
want to join just recite on different
machines and then you have a forced
latency to get them together by all
communications and so therefore the way
people have to massage the data into
tables to use the relational model
successfully is in direct contradiction
to high efficiency when you shout
there is no sequel database you have
other possibilities you have possibility
to embed stuff you have two possibility
to have more flexible data models to
make the sharding such that the
performance of the queries is better I
see so it's basically the normalization
of data in in a relational database
which comes in the way of scaling it
successfully when it when compared to a
no sequel database yes that's the one
thing the other thing is once you do
sequel you have to be fully acid
compliant because the standards donators
prescribes that and that's another thing
which is in some kind of resistance
against ability great so we talked about
what is polyglot persistence can you
tell me what are the benefits an
overhead of a polyglot persistence
scenario right the benefits is you can
use the right data model in all places
therefore your queries tend to be very
efficient and you have to do probably
less data conversion to massage
to the forward which is actually stored
in the database let's to birdwatcher to
silence a high-performance easy data
modelling because there's a lot of
flexibility now if you for example take
a document store it will usually be
schema-less so one disadvantage with the
schema business it gives you great
flexibility but if you are not careful
then you will have a very dirty data
which is not very uniform and difficult
to work with so I always say yes
usually it's schema-less but in the end
there has to be a schema otherwise you
cannot really probably work with the
data now when it then comes to
implementation if you need to start to
need multiple data stores for your
different data offers then you have a
consistency problem because you might
have to store the same data in two
different data stores and this means you
cannot have a transaction spanning both
of them so therefore you have to work
hard on the client side to keep the two
copies of the data in sync and to keep
them consistent so you have more
consistency furthermore you have more
technological overheads if you will use
three data stores in a project you have
to pay three times license fees you have
to pay three times for support or to
teach your people three times to use a
product and you have to have to have to
work with maybe three different
providers and have three different
manuals to work and that has additional
operational costs and so therefore I
like the definition of polyglot
persistence of using the right data
model because this now opens the door to
use a multi model database to have both
benefits you have the flexibility of
data modeler and the high performance
where your queries and yet you don't
need three different data stores but
maybe get away with one or maybe two and
that is why multi model is in my opinion
so attractive it can lower costs it can
speed up the call the developments and
coming back to the example of e-commerce
website which we discussed while
discussing about different types of no
sequel databases how would I do the same
thing in a multi modal database and at
the same time giving the guarantee that
the data is not stored in a redundant
fashion yeah this is a very very good
question if you have the wrong type of
multimodal database you might actually
have that problem
because there is something I call native
multi modal databases a native model to
model database you have multiple data
models supported in both the storage and
in the query but it's not actually held
in redundant copies but if you take for
example a remote EP essentially we store
all the data in documents so essentially
we use the document model however to be
to be a successful graph database at the
same time what we do is yes our vertices
are documents and the edges of the
graphs are documents as well but we have
very very efficient special indexes to
find the edges which are adjacent to a
vertex because that is the fundamental
operation you need engrafted errors you
need to very very quickly tell what are
the neighbors what are the adjacent
edges and what are the neighbors of a
vertex but if you reuse the document
model and essentially put the right
indexes and query implementations in
place then you can do this natively and
that same
when combined k-value and so therefore
these three data models which we are
using document database graph database
and key value fit together in a union
they fit together subset the data does
not have to be duplicated that it's just
to have different query engine switch
which query the data according to the
data model and can then also be combined
in the same village I say I see so we
will discuss more about how Arango DB
makes it possible but before we go over
there I quickly wanted to discuss one
thing in episode 218 we did a show on
CQRS which is the command query
responsibilities saturations
which basically means you design your
data model in such a way that your right
and your reads are going to two
different data stores so that right can
scale better than and they do not are
not bottleneck by the reads
so how would you I mean if it's even
possible compare multimodal database
with the CQRS style of data modeling
yeah I would say tries to prevent the
complexity you get by putting the writes
in one place and getting the reads from
novels so by combining this and leaving
everything in the same engine yes you
have to have some compromises obviously
if you have a very very heavy right load
it might slow down your reads that's
right but on the other hand you have all
the complain you lose the complexity of
having to move the data from the place
where you wrote it to the place where
you read it from so I would imagine that
both technologies have good use cases
but I think the difference is that you
are worth is complexity the cost of
potentially yeah lower performance with
you to both writers writes and reads I
see yeah I think in that in that manner
CQRS
same kind of bottlenecks like a polyglot
persistence model in which we have to
work pretty hard to keep the rights
synced with the read so that the read
queries don't serve stale data so now
that we have brought Arango DB we have
discussed about multimodal databases and
briefly about rango DB I just wanted to
understand that rango D from the website
I saw that Arango DB supports three
different models which are document key
value and graph why does Arango DB only
support these three models of no sequel
database and no other which we discussed
earlier in the show now that's a very
good question
we seek a relatively earlier the process
that these three tiida models fit
together around the web if you will say
you take it optional store and treat it
as a key value store that is you don't
use secondary indexes on your wellness
then you are nearly there so so those
two come together pretty well but the
graph that arises I explained earlier
also fits quite well because with the
right index and the right bra traversal
engine you can use the document model
and still have an efficient graph
database if you look at other data
models like time series or columnist on
they don't really work well with the
first three so therefore they are if we
wanted to support that which would not
be impossible but we would then run into
these problems that the data models
don't fit together well and you
essentially have to decide in which kind
of format to store so that's the
decision we didn't have to do for these
three data models but for conv or for
time seriously would have to store in a
different way and then we lose this
these advantages to be a native multi
model database and would be essentially
back to political processes with
multiple let us toss okay in one package
question I think that that's a good
point that for a multi modal database
the different models have to be somewhat
related to each other such that you
don't have to again come back to storing
data in a redundant fashion and lose all
the good things which multi modal
database brings yeah so you just
mentioned about rango dB
being a native multi modal database and
there are certain databases out there
which have a layered multi-modal
approach so can you tell me what is the
difference between a native database and
a layered it layered native multi modal
database and the layered multi bottle
database yeah so what layouts multiple
databases to is they essentially
implement one theta model as the lowest
layer typically a solid key value store
and then they put on top of that a
separate layer which for example might
implement documents or might implement
graphs or whatever now from an
architectural standpoint that's a good
idea because it separates things nicely
and it separates these layers and it
looks quite neat if you however then
consider a high performance then you
find out that suddenly the upper layers
have to know about the intricacies of
the lower layer and the lower layer has
to be prepared to support the right
theories for the high opinion and you
either really very much interlink for to
then you are essentially back at the
native multi metal moral database which
has all in one package or you sacrifice
performance and that is why we have
chosen to go the native multi modal way
to really integrate everything into one
engine with very unique with a common
query language which allows to mix and
match those data models even in one
theory right so can you briefly explain
just to establish for the listener a
clear understand difference between
native and layered multi bottle what
exactly makes rango DB a native
multi-model
is it the way the data is stored in the
storage engine in a non redundant
fashion that makes Arango DB a native
multi model yeah what it makes it native
is that the three data models we support
are all implemented in the same core
with the same query engine and optimizer
and don't need any kind of redundant
store or separation of concerns in a
layered approach you would have one
fundamental data model which underlies
everything which is the core
implementation and then you would have
on top other features but most of the
time performance cannot be as good as
with an integrated solution
I see yep because on while I was
researching on this topic I came across
documentation which mentioned that each
document of Arango DB collection has
these native underscore two and
underscore from underscore ID and
underscore key attributes which are used
to establish relationships between one
model between two different multiple
three different models which we have
from that I kind of got an idea that
that's how Arango DB is basically
preventing storing the data in a
redundant fashion yeah that's right so
once you have h documents you have the
from and the two has built-in attributes
which are also enforced and in the sense
this is a kind of schema and since we
know that this is a reg collection we
know that they exist and we can be
pretty quick with the indexing and with
the finding of neighbors and that is
essentially what makes the graph engine
tick on top of the Delft they're not on
top but integrated with the document
storage
great so now that we have this curve
about some basics of rango DB I wanted
to deep dive into an Rango DB cluster
because that's one of the important use
case which brings out the power power of
any multimodal database so can you
briefly or maybe elaborately described
different components of a Rango DB
cluster yeah so first of all as an
overview the rangatira cluster is fully
fault tolerant it does not have a single
point of failure so how do we achieve
that essentially in the center of the
cluster is an arrangement of usually
three or five special Arango tea
instances which we call the agency and
which is a highly redundant and fault
tolerant key value store using the rafts
consensus protocol so that is where we
keep the cluster configuration and that
is where the failover algorithms and
redundancy algorithms actually
implemented so that is not the part
which does the high performance data
manipulation so that is essentially you
should be mentioned that central part
the agency as a slow key value store
just for the cluster configuration but
it's so that I think they cool and
open-source equivalent of that when we
zookeeper for example that is right
okay that that's a good point set up
cell you have etcd as such a central
component for example for Zucco for
kubernetes and for example Kafka uses
zookeeper in exactly the same way as we
use our raft and sam'l soap which is
created with wrong with itself and apart
from that we have two different type of
instances there is so called database
service and the coordinators and they
play very different roles the database
servers then hold the bulk of the data
perform
application and also for the queries
performed upon the work for the query
engine the coordinators they take the
grind requests and are aware of the
structure of a cluster by talking to the
agency and do the query optimization and
distribution in the trustor and then
work with the database service tools to
fulfill the actual queries so every
client request comes into one of the
coordinators and you can choose an
arbitrary one because that is fault
tolerance in that one latvia and so that
gives you a scalable layer doing query
optimization and talking to clients
requests and independently from this you
can scale the database server layer by
adding more capacity for queries and
more capacity for data and so everything
you sent to the database goes to a
coordinator it assembles the right data
pipeline within the trustor talk by
talking to some database servers and in
the end the result will again be sent
out to a form the coordinator to your to
enough language that's the basic
structure here for the components like
for example for monitoring we have
sidekick contain us to export mitosis
matrix and we have a separate system to
do tennis and tennis and the replication
that is all running in separate pots in
kubernetes are swirling in several
processes if you run without philetus
and so that essentially all together
makes up the complete cluster system but
the basic thing is the coordinators on
the side of the service I see so I think
that's a good thing that she brought up
that these two components coordinators
and the database server kind of
separates I mean kind of makes scaling
the storage and the compute
separately easier because if there's a
clean separation of course coordinator
and the database server so if there is
no more load on the system read load for
example you could perhaps just add more
coordinator nodes because that's where
that's the first
layer four first component which where
the query hits and if there is more
storage load then you can add the
database servers exactly great so I
wanted to quickly talk a little bit
about database database servers so there
are two different kinds of database
server if I'm not wrong the primary
database server and the secondary
database server primary are the ones
which supports synchronous replication
of writes so I wanted to understand that
the when for a primary database server
when the replication happens the
synchronous replication happens from a
leader to a follower what happens when
the follower is not available since it's
synchronous replication how does how do
we do we acknowledge the right or do we
fail the right what happens okay that's
a very good question this we might be
hard to come back to the second or is
later because in the latest version
along with TP we do no longer have them
but about synchronous replication of
this is handled by the primary database
it was in its handle in the following
world if you configure the replication
factor for collection to be say three
then this means that there is the leader
thus the primary who has the primary
copy of the data and two copies that is
to follow us The Rave right first goes
to the leader that's the primary which
has the primary copy of the data and
it's synchronously replicated before we
tell the client that the right is
actually acknowledged so it is
replicated to every replicas before we
go back to the client and tell about
success now if a client if a database
server which is a follower becomes
unavailable we can temporarily drop that
follower and say this is no longer in
sync so that happens after a time out of
the few seconds so if this is if the
server is a few seconds away
then this database will decide for now I
will no longer replicate to that replica
and still confirm that I have the data
now obviously behind the scenes when the
server comes back it's automatically
brought back in sync such that future
requests can then again be done in a
circular fashion and that was if the
leader has a failover with the leader
fails then there is something in the
agency which essentially fails over this
leadership to one of the followers which
is currently in second and so that means
that in either case you have just asked
a few seconds that you have I see so if
a follower fails then for a replication
factor of three so we make the right to
two of the replicas and go forward
acknowledge that acknowledge the client
is that correct yes and then in the
background we have some kind of an anti
entropy tool which brings the the
replica which has fallen behind up to
date when that node for example comes up
that's right but in most cases this is
not necessary because the replication
can happen sooner honestly and if
there's no delay then pastille then we
wait until all right because have
replicated the data
okay so you mentioned about secondary
database servers and from what I
understand they are they they are the
ones which get the asynchronous
replication stream from the primary
database server and are used as backups
so how far behind is the stream I mean
how far behind are the the secondary
database server from the primary
database server because this is
asynchronous replication yeah so all for
the
faster version of our on TV with the
currently published versions these
secondaries do no longer exist
okay the synthesis on chemistry we could
never really make guarantees to not lose
data at a failover and so therefore we
has we have for the cluster and polished
that now for a single server you can
still use a synchronous replication to
replicate essentially every right to a
second instance and that is awesome
promise and is usually behind if you
have a fast network of the area of
milliseconds so it's still pretty good
but obviously we cannot make any
guarantees if the primary fails then
your representing card just does not
have all the data okay we have a special
deployment mode which we call active
failover where we exploit this kind of
technology and they are we still have
the primaries of the secondaries or we
call them leader and follower again here
and there you have an automatic failover
and you can put a load balancer in front
of that but still you cannot guarantee
there's no data loss in case the media
fails and on top of all that for the
cluster which at this stage only does
synchronous replication as discussed we
have a further datacenter to datacenter
replication which sits on top of the
cluster and that is also a centralized
in nature and here the idea is that
people whose the cluster and sudras
replication within a data center to have
a resilient data store there but for
completely disaster recovery scenarios
like really a complete data center
failing or going up in flames
they use data center data center
replication yes it is a some class but
since it's highly scalable it's also
usually on the order of magnitudes of
milliseconds behind and so therefore
most of the data is still there which is
mostly good enough for disaster recovery
scenario I see and I believe this
feature of inter data center
synchronous replication is currently
available only in the Enterprise Edition
that is true of our enterprise features
we carefully try to make it so that the
community version is fully functional
and can actually be used in production
without motion restrictions and we
figured that this kind of disaster
recovery scenario is mostly used by
began to crisis make sense so one last
aspect of rango DB cluster which I
wanted to discuss was as to where it
stands when it I think we briefly talked
about it but where it stands
when it comes to cap theorem from what I
understand it's it's consistency and
consistency and network partition the CP
more than ap side of things is that
correct that is absolutely correct there
is an intention in the intentional
decision we made to make it distributed
but of the CP count remember can prevent
network partitions and in case of a
partition we value consistency over
ability and from documentation I it says
that and the cluster Arango DB cluster
has a master master model does that mean
that the same shot of data is stored on
two different masters served by two
different master servers and if there is
a conflict then we have some sort of a
conflict resolution and not really so
this master master master slave is in my
opinion a big buzzword and what we have
chosen is a middle ground between the
two extremes yes one can truly say that
we are master to master master because
you can essentially write or read from
any coordinator and you always get the
same consistent result so in that sense
from a client perspective it is master
master
because you can simply write to
everybody and you can use a load balance
up front and it is all fine entirely
resentment behind the scenes we choose
for efficiency and consistency reasons a
master/slave model where we say for
every single shot of our collection at
all times one database server is the
leader for that chart and the others are
followers now you are the customer you
don't notice that because you talked to
any of the coordinators and it will at
all times
redirect your requests to the right
leader that will replicate it to the
followers and without you noticing you
gather the response that everything is
fine if that leader fails behind the
scenes again we'd replace it by a
completely instant replica and that very
same coordinator you are talking to will
instantly switch over from now on to
talk to the other leader and so without
noticing to the outside world we have
failed over and have to switch leader
and follower and therefore the whole
solution is essentially isomorphic to a
master master thing but we don't have
the problem of confidence because they
can never arise every single right goes
through the current leader and we can
serialize rise to the collection in this
way and therefore we can never have a
kind of college called contradiction or
conflict arise right so yeah that's what
I also gathered that the terminology of
master master was used because any node
could technically take right for any
shard and not because that we there are
two different leaders for the same shard
which would which would I guess make
things go on the AP on the AP side
rather than CP side of things yes this
kind of conflict resolution in the end
surface to the customer so the next
moving on I wanted to discuss about the
storage engines
which are used in Arango DB but before
that can you define what is a storage
engine yeah there's a general very good
question forces are clear we call the
storage engine the machinery which
underlies a single database server to
persist the data to its disk so a
storage engine is very much note local
thing for us and it works best if it's
actually attached to local storage like
a local SSD and currently I think I can
move on immediately currently we have
two storage engines and you can
configure you are arauco it says to use
either one of them one is the one we had
first which is called mm files
it is a user's memory mapped files but
it does all indexing in memory so
therefore it is optimized for cases
where all your data fit into RAM
including the indexes and it is very
high performance then the second storage
engine we offer is based on rocks DB so
we simply use the rocks TV library from
Facebook on each database server to
persist the data and as you might know
rocks TP is itself sorted key value
store so therefore we realize all the
indexes including the h-index and all
the data storage within rocks to be
based on its key value model and that is
optimized for the case that not only our
data fits into run and it's very good in
keeping a hot set in memory and still
allowing you to use the full capacity of
your locally attached SSD or disk I see
right so I think like the indexes which
are in Arango DB the behavior and what
kind of queries I can make against them
is tightly coupled with what kind of
storage engine which I am using in the
background is that a correct statement
that is correct although as much of that
as possible so we
the same name so for example you can
still create a hash index even on Ross
to me but in the end behind the scenes
it's it's a key lookup it rock Sleepy
where it ends but they should behave
identical but the details of the
performance are different depending on
the storage engine right so like from
what I understand if the like you
mentioned in Roxby be the keys are so
stored as sorted key value pairs which
makes doing range queries much easier of
much faster if you have a rocks DB
storage engine as compared to an mm file
storage engine is that correct that's
not quite correct because as a
replacement for event files yes we have
the persistence just in memory mapped
files and essentially append-only store
but if you need range queries we have a
skip list index in memory so there can
you can probably even faster traverse
your range query and hook up reg sorted
indexes part of course the index and the
sorted thing has to fit into memory I
say so now that we are talking about
indexes one special one index which I
was particularly interested in
discussing is the edge index which is
basically the the core data structure
which is used for serving any kind of
graph query can you describe what does
an edge index look like in Arango dB
yes so the key role the h-index plays is
that we have an edge collection there is
a collection of documents which contains
all these edges and since they are from
attribute describes where from which
vertex the edge is coming from
we need to very very quickly find all
the edges which come from a given vertex
so that essentially means we need a very
fast index on the from attribute for the
edge
collection and the same with the tool
collection if you want to go edges in a
backward direction having said that it's
not only necessary that we find all the
edges quickly but also it must be we
must be able to update that in this
quickly for example if you remove for an
edge and imagine you have something like
a super node where you have a vertex
which has a million outgoing edges you
still must be able to remove an edge
pretty quickly even if it is incident
with that super node and that makes the
data structure for the edge index
interesting because it can essentially
insert and and remove a simple edge in
constant time but it can list you all
the edges incident with the vertex in
time which is proportional to the number
of edges in the result and that is the
crucial ingredient now just one more
word for rocks to be rusty B we use
essentially assorted unless on the forum
attribute here but to make this very
very high performant we have in front of
rocks D being a special cash sitting
which can answer this question about the
adjacent lyndah adjacent vertices and
edges very very quickly once it has been
asked before and that is particularly
interesting because rock CB is a
transactional key value store so the
challenge they are was to find a data
structure in memory which can cache the
result of such a range query setting and
still give you other transactional
semantics of rocks to be so particular
it needs to be a cache hit if the
transaction with which you're reading
this still would produce the right
result and it has to invalidate the
cache if you start a new transaction
where this doesn't count anymore yeah
that's definitely interesting eggs since
we are talking about the graph indexes
and and and next I want to talk about
transaction but before going over there
I just wanted to emphasize that this is
where
the power of a multimodal database lies
the edge index helps and performing
graph queries in an order of number of
neighbors rather than doing going while
looking doing index lookup in each while
performing a join in a relational
database style fashion when we are
serving a query which has like a query
of graph graph nature I think that's
where the power of a graph database lies
that it is basically able to get all my
neighbors in an order of number of
neighbors without doing any any more
than necessary index lookups yes that's
absolutely right and there's one more
aspect I would like to mention here in
case you have interests which many edges
which are adjacent with the same vertex
you have a separate problem because
quite often you don't want to see all
these address coming out of this vertex
but maybe you want to filter on some
kind of timestamp and just take the
outgoing edges say you have a simple
note and the million edges coming out of
the node and you just want to see those
ten which fulfill a certain condition of
the time step then you need a concept
called vertex centric indexes which
means that you essentially not only have
the edge of X but you also have a kind
of index on the set of edges coming out
of the single vortex because then you
can very very quickly home in into
exactly those fewer edges you need and
that is actually for a certain type of
graph traversal is also quite important
and that we essentially do by using
sorted indexes which first sort by the
from attribute and then by potentially
other attributes I say great so let's
move on to the transaction
Oh DB so the documentation of Arango DB
states that it provides multi document
and multi collection transaction on a
single instance of Wrangell DB how does
a tango DB ensure that yeah for a simple
instance we have a transactional storage
engine because the true storage engine
is now the storage engine for the
complete database and so therefore we
can use either the transactional
facilities of rock's TP or we can use
the transactional features of the MM
file storage engine to directly provide
full acid semantics for multiple
multiple collection operations in a
cluster it's not quite that easy because
although the storage engine we have is
transactional with transactional the
single database server and so therefore
at this stage I'm unhappy to say but I
have to say that we only offer asset
guarantees in a cluster for single
document operations so the otama CT here
is on a single document because a single
document will always be on a single
document shard leader and so therefore
we can enforce that however we have
plans to implement distributed
transactions and one of my big dreams is
that I see this headline on Hacker News
around V now with distributed
transactions once I see that I'm happy
man great yeah definitely that will be
something to have or distribute to have
distributed transactions because they
are not easy to implement so just so
that the listener gets a clear
understanding of how the transaction
work in rango DB can you discuss the
read write and exclusive collection
types which are specified by the client
which is making a query how how do they
fit in this transaction model there
currently you get two ways to execute
transactions in TV land recall this is
trust in the single instance one way is
to use the EQ and
mostly a rainbow query language which is
by definition transactional so if you do
read you will always see a consistent
snapshot with one read transaction if
you do have writing the thing that this
will always be a signal transaction
unless it becomes too big and we have to
do intermediate permits because of
limitations so therefore or a single
instance this happens behind the scenes
in a QL a second possibility is that you
send a JavaScript function and recall
that we embed the Kuhl's v8 JavaScript
engine
you send a JavaScript function which
essentially executes as a transaction so
all the manipulations that function does
to your data are physically wrapped into
a transaction and if the whole thing
fails or throws an exception then
everything is aborted and the
transaction is aborted and if it ends
normally then it's committed and the
transaction is finished and has
committed so that's the model for
transactions we have currently and but
when we move to trust our white
transactions we will probably have a
model where you use an API call to start
a transaction and then you perform
multiple operations within the context
of that transaction and in the end you
send either commit or abort so that is
something we will probably move to but
that is not currently there I see so
anytime and Arango DB transaction is
performed it announces that which all
collections it will be using in read
mode write mode or exclusive mode so
when we are serving let's say a graph
query where we don't know what all
collections we will end up making the
query on just because of the the nature
of the graph is it possible that we
enter into a deadlock and if that does
happen how can wrangle DB recover from
it yeah
so that's this particular reason we
and we require that you name all the
collections you want to use in a graph
traversal before you actually use them
because otherwise we could not prevent
that kind of deadlock from happening
so in particular in a distributed system
that would be disastrous and so
therefore we can do data protection
against that and this doesn't have but
you have two men to name all the
collections which appear in your Rafi
the most situations you will have one
word list collection and one edge
collection for the wrath and it will not
actually be a problem but you can't have
use multiple etching multiple motors
collections and then you simply have to
name them I see so one last question on
transactions which I had so that the
listener kind of gets an idea of how
transaction works for for a clustered
environment rango DB currently suppose
single document distributed transactions
is that correct that is right and you
have to kind of compare and swap
operation so you can say this right over
is only to be executed provided the
current version of the document is this
one I see
so do we are we using like a two-phase
commit kind of protocol to enforce that
no we don't have to because the shaft
leader for every shot is responsible to
serialize and to ensure the atomicity of
the document operation for that
particular shaft I see
so but if that transaction is is
happening on is across multiple nodes so
then how do we ensure that all the nodes
in the in the participating in that
transaction are in sync do you kind of
get what I'm getting getting on
transactions with single documents we
perform the transaction on the shot
leader and synchronously replicate
to all replicas before we tell the
customer yes this transaction has
happened the chart leader see realises
the operations for that particular shot
and the replicas just do the same
transactions one after another and this
comes back to the other thing we covered
provided some of the followers fail they
are temporarily dropped as instant
follow us and we can move on and later
the system will repair itself by
synchronizing with inter trust oh great
so now that we have discussed many
aspects of a wrangle db1 one of the last
things which I wanted to discuss was the
horizontal scaling of a Rango DB since
we support three different models in
Arango DB how are the challenges
different for different model when it
comes to scaling that is very good
question so for the key value it's
trivial you simply scale and there's no
problem charlie is done in a hash based
fashion and then that is not for
documents it depends on the query if you
trust to a simple document lookup sauce
or use a simple secondary index it works
equally well secondary index or a
Charlotte collection is nothing but an
index on each chart and so we can just
use the usual indexing locally and then
put the results together of the
coordinator but when it comes to more
complex queries like John operations and
so on then yes scalability is a
challenge so for this particular purpose
we do our best to make our query
optimizer are aware of this and in the
Enterprise version we have something
called celluloid collections that is a
feature where you can take a relatively
small collection and simply say you are
a satellite collection you are
replicated in a centralized fashion to
every single node in the trustor
this means that a join operation
between that satellite collection and a
larger Charlotte collection can be
pretty fast because it can be done
locally on each shard of the large
collection because a copy of the small
collection is available everywhere des
centrally so that feature enables us to
scale better in a lot of cases where
complicated tour operations would
otherwise be a challenge
now the late the last document a storage
model is for its for graphs and here
scaling is particularly difficult to
mention a graph which is just in some
kind of random fashion distributed all
over the place
you want to run a graph traversal you
have to hop between nodes in an
incredible fashion and it becomes
awfully slow and you know looking up an
edge or something like that in local
storage can be as fast as a few hundred
nanoseconds whereas the network op can
be a thousand or 10,000 times slower so
that is really really a big challenge
and we addressed that with a feature
called Smart graphs which is again only
in the enterprise version which does
essentially the follow me most of the
time you have to make specific knowledge
to be able to sharp your graph in a
better way such that most edges are
actually neutral on your notes and the
shot graph shot a smart graphic
limitation makes use of that fact the
user has to give a so-called smartcraft
attribute which is then used to do the
Sharlee of the vertices and edges across
your cluster and if this has been done
properly most edges are local and our
algorithms for graph traversal make use
of that fact by essentially doing as
much as possible of the transversal on
each local node and only reporting
results when we have to do jumps between
nodes that can speed up a graph
traversal spyin typically effect
of 10 or 100 and is what we do to scale
craft reversals which in principle are
challenged for scaling right that's a
pretty interesting couple of things
which you mentioned about smart graphs
and the satellite collections satellite
collections to to kind of scale the
document store and the smart graph to
scale the graph the graph model of side
of the multimodal database so the last
question because you're having out of
time is is regarding the performance
comparison I on the website looking at
the graphs which we're comparing rango
DB with other multimodal database and
also the single model databases
Arango DB seem to be doing at least as
well as all those how do those numbers
look like in a clustered setting yeah
and in a setting we have done
comparisons as well but mostly using
relatively simple queries so in the
charset query you are you are interested
on whether single document operations or
single document lookups of writes scale
well and we have demonstrated in one
performance benchmark that we can really
linearly scale with a number of
instances yes smart graphs and certain
operations are good but you can never
expect trivial scalability you can ever
say with ten times the machines I'm ten
times as fast this is simply there are
theoretical limits to that and so
therefore and the other thing is it's
it's actually difficult there's not that
many distributed graph databases there's
not that many distributed data stores
which can actually do complex operations
and so on so therefore the chrome to
cover with Spanish boxes they are a bit
Xena great so I think at this point of
time we are at the end of the show is
there something which you would like to
say to the audience or
if there's something which you feel I
did not ask but you wanted to cover
there's actually two things I just would
like to mention briefly because people
can then look up then first of all we
have JavaScript framework to actually
deploy extensions to the database
directly to the database server I know
our mentioned that we embed v8 the
Google v8 engine
so our Fox framework allows that you can
actually extend the api of the database
with your own javascript code that gives
a lot of possibilities like a schema
enforcing like a very flexible design of
your microservices and so on I don't
want to go into much detail that
framework is running on the coordinators
and can be scaled independently from the
database servers in this way and it's
also a great extension for ability and
the second thing I want to mention is
that deployment has become particularly
easy now because we have a kubernetes
operator so that means essentially
deploying an around EB cluster with
replication and everything and metrics
and so on becomes essentially as easy to
assess you install an app on your phone
because you just take a little gobble
file of ten lines and deploy to your
kubernetes cluster and suddenly
everything is fired up and works like
magic there will be no more about this
in our publications but these are the
two things I really wanted to mention
great great yeah I wanted to discuss the
Fox framework but we are running out of
time so I did not get a chance to deep
dive into it but maybe I can invite you
some other time and we can discuss other
aspects of a wrangle DB which we were
not able to cover today so max how can
people follow you well first of all we
have a blog on the Arango DB page where
I occasionally write stuff we have the
wrong to be twitter account which is
just a drawing TP and that is
interesting stuff as a newsletter
as form and essentially my complete work
is on github so therefore the most of
the work is done in the open-source
version and one can see what I do I also
have slides on SlideShare I myself
personally not very active on Twitter I
have to admit just finding no what no
not it not the time to do that okay I'll
include all the necessary links so that
people can follow you in the in the show
outline so max thank you for coming on
the show this is Mission San Asia from
software engineering radio thank you all
for listening and thanks thanks for
listening the se radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website that will reach us on
LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our
slack channel at SC radio.com
you can also email us at team at SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
se radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening